So, every single day there are new AI
search rank trackers popping up and so
many of them are making some pretty wild
claims and I just want to put some kind
of misconceptions to rest here and this
is very important when you're trying to
decide what rank tracker you want to
use. Now, one thing I will say is that
you should be tracking your brand's
performance inside of chat GBT and the
large language models and also Google's
new AI products like AI mode and AI
overview. So, you should be tracking.
The problem is is just some of the
claims that are being made that just
simply are not true. So, let's dive
right into it. First, there's tons of
money being plowed into this industry
right now. And basically, this industry,
you you know, we can kind of segment it
out as AI tracking as far as tracking
your brand mentions inside of generated
responses inside of AI platforms and
then also tracking citations. So, the
actual links that appear when the AI
goes and retrieves information and then
cites that source. Okay, so these
companies I'm showing here, this isn't
like some indictment on these
specifically. I just pulled these random
screenshots cuz I know they got funding.
And also, just to clarify, um this is
not an indictment on every tool that's
out there. It's just a couple key things
I've seen. I won't be naming names
either. I just want to make sure though
that if you're trying to make an
educated decision about investing in one
of these tools, you need to you need to
kind of know some of the details. And
so, as of right now, the average cost
for an AI tracking tool is about $337
per month. We did we studied uh over 30
of these tools. The average is about
$337 per month, which is pretty
significant. It's not it's not a small
investment. So, you should be aware of
some of these details. So, let's get
into it. So, this is the first claim
that I've seen pop up on a few different
websites, okay? And this one is one of
the worst, okay? Which is, you know,
explore keyword and topic volume across
AI platforms. Okay? So just to be very
clear, there is no possible way that
anyone, any company, any person has
access to any type of real search demand
on chat GBT or on any large language
model. They do not share this
information with anyone. There isn't
this isn't like Google where you can go
to Google search console and you can
freely see the searches that are being
conducted in Google. That does not exist
for any of these platforms. So any tool
that's claiming that they have real
demand data, it's just not true. There
there it's literally impossible to have
that data. It does not exist. And in
fact, chat GBT has intentionally not
given that data because of the fear that
it's going to be abused. So, and you
know, maybe that'll change in the future
and hopefully it does. I hope that these
LLMs give access to more data so that
marketers can actually, you know, start
to use these platforms better. But right
now, no one has access to this data. So,
anyone that's showing you search volume
data um is really just pulling from
search volume from the traditional
searches. So, you know, going into
Google keyword planner and extract using
their API to pull that data. Um that
that's basically what's going on. So, in
in essence, they're mirroring demand,
but it's not true demand. Okay? It's not
true demand of what people are actually
searching in these platforms. It's a
very important point. So be careful if
you see any tool claiming to have this
type of demand vault, you know, this
demand data. Uh same thing with this.
Discover what millions of people ask on
AI. Once again, no one knows this
information. It does not exist. Trust
me, if it existed, I would be using it.
It does not exist. Um no one has access
to this information. Uh and so just be
careful with this claim. And then the
most, this is kind of the third one
here, which is just too much conviction
about the accuracy of the data. If you
look at a lot of these AI trackers, they
claim to have, you know, the keys to the
kingdom, but the truth is that, as I'm
about to show you, getting reliable,
accurate data as far as tracking is
really, really hard in these platforms.
This is not like traditional rank
tracking that's existed for over a
decade that I've been doing SEO where
you put your keyword into a rank tracker
and you see how that page performs over
time. That's much easier because the the
uh the variance in search results is not
that significant in traditional search.
like couple spots here and there, not
significant. Then, you know, maybe a a
Google update will come around and that
obviously changes the game and there's
significant variance, but for the most
part, like it didn't move that much. So,
you could actually track it, you know,
week over week, month over month,
quarter over quarter and see kind of
where things are falling. This is
radically different as you're about to
see. Okay, so why tracking gathering uh
reliable data is really, really hard. So
let's kind of dive into this. Number one
is extreme variance. No two queries are
the same. Now this may have been the
case with Google because Google does
consolidate queries together to give you
kind of this broader search volume. But
this is next level because almost
everyone who's using chat GBT or any
LLM, they are really putting in their
own unique, you know, queries. And it's
not like they're just searching, you
know, best blue shoes. Like most people
aren't searching like that on these
platforms. It's going to be unique.
There's going to be grammatical errors.
They're going to be sentences. Sometimes
dissertations. Some people are using
voice search. Some people are not. Just
the variance in queries is enormous. And
so there is a way to kind of to to
handle this, but this is one variable
that's going to make it very difficult
to get reliable data.
The the next one is personalization.
Okay. So like we're looking at my
account here. And when I search in my
account, not in a a private window, um,
chat GBT knows who I am because of my
account, right? So I have the
personalization turned on and most
people do because by default
personalization is turned on. So that
means the large large majority of people
that are using chat GBT are seeing that
personalized experience. And the problem
is chat GBT in particular is really
nice, right? It's always nice about your
ideas and your business and your
products. So, what it will do oftent
times is I'll show you in a second. If
you say if you search within your your
standard searches in your account
without um a private window or a private
search, it's going to say that your
product ranks for a lot of things,
right? If you say, "What are the best
SEO content optimization tools?" It's
going to say, "Yeah, rankability is
right in there." Right? It's going to
say that because that's what it wants.
it it thinks that's what it wants me to
hear, right? So, it is designed to be
very positive in that regard and it's
not very objective in many ways. And so,
the point is is like that already
muddies the waters massively with the
personalization. What you see when you
uh run a query through an API or you run
a query through an incognito search is
radically different than what a user's
actually going to experience in the
platform. And so until we actually get
real data about this, we're all just
kind of guessing. And so personalization
really is a dramatic one. That's why I
put it very early here because it's it
is truly the one that makes tracking so
incredibly difficult because every
person's experience, and this is
actually if you watch what Sam Alman,
the founder of OpenAI, has talked about,
he wants it to be like your personal
assistant that's highly personalized to
you specifically, right? That is going
to cause some challenges with tracking.
model variants. Okay, just in chat GBT
alone, we see how many different models
you can pick from. 1 2 3 4 5 6 seven
different models. Now, I don't think
this is going to be the case forever. I
think there's going to be some
consolidation of models and maybe have
like one universal model that does kind
of everything reasoning and you know all
you know multi- multimod you know
multi-use case type of model but in
general right now the models are very
different and funny enough when you run
queries across each individual model run
the same exact query okay you will get
different results it's pretty crazy I'll
show you an example of
So check this out. So this is I ran uh
what are the best SEO content
optimization tools right now. Okay, so I
intentionally used right now so it would
try to pull from search and retrieve
that information. But funny enough for
40 For it actually didn't retrieve
anything. It just did straight uh you
know straight answer in this regard. Now
once again it's putting rankability in
here. This is my account. So I can't
trust this. I cannot trust that it did
that this is true. Um it's telling me
what I want to hear, right? So I don't
trust it. Uh but you can see here this
you know this these are kind of
generally the answers that you'll get.
But then we run this through uh 04 mini
we get a very different set of results
right pretty similar pretty similar and
I'll say this is why you want to have a
lot of uh prompt diversity and there's
some other methods we can use but once
again you know pretty pretty different
and plus it retrieved on this one. So,
it actually went out and searched to
enhance the prompting for this
particular, you know, topic. Once again,
I'm using the same exact seed though.
This is the same seed and running it
across different uh, you know, different
different models and getting pretty
different results uh, and even in
different, you know, in a temporary
chat. So, I ran this across all the
different models and we are starting to
see some similarities, but once again,
this is just one of those things where
it's just going to add some some stuff
here that's just going to make it more
challenging to actually get reliable
data. Okay? Just because there's so much
variance with these answers, okay? And
then the responses that you get
obviously are almost always different.
Like you run the same exact query, you
get a different response. Now, are the
brands that show up going to be pretty
similar? Yeah, typically. They're going
to be kind of similar. It's not always
going to be in the same exact position.
It's not always going to be in the same
exact format, but the responses are
different different typically. There's
nothing that's cookie cutter uh based on
what I've seen and I've been using chat
GPD since it came out in November 2022.
So, I've been using it for a long time
and I can tell you very rarely would you
ever see a response that's exactly the
same. I never see that. Um and then
queries the even the queries that are
used like in the 03 model if we go here
into the 03 model or even 04 actually
let's try to find one that where it did
some significant reasoning uh so like
here you can see the queries in the
query fan out here if we inspect you'll
see that what it uses here to actually
go and search and retrieve information
to make its responses more reliable and
more accurate and more timely. It
changes that all the time. It's pretty
it it's similar usually on the first
seed that it does. So like if you do
something like I did, it's usually going
to search kind of some sort of listical
type of query like this that has a year
modifier on it. But when it starts to
fan out and it starts to go and and
introduce new queries into this to kind
of, you know, uh ampl to enhance that
response and make it more accurate, it
changes a lot. there's not kind of like
there are some general formats that it
uses that some patterns but it does it
it's pretty significantly different on
most queries once again so there's just
a lot of a lot of variance on these
things and that's why when I say don't
have too much conviction about what's
going on here this is what I mean
because there's just so many possible
variations going on okay so responses
are almost always different uh the types
queries that are used in the reasoning
models for query fan out are almost
there there are some templates and
patterns but they tend to be pretty
different for the most part. And then
citations. Once again, you can look here
in the citations and see that yeah, we
see some similarities in these
citations, like a couple here and there,
but once again, there is significant
variance even in the citations that are
used um in this process, right?
Sometimes there's a ton of citations,
sometimes there's very little. Sometimes
they're using Reddit, other times
they're not, right? There's so there
there's just a lot of variance. Now the
good news is even when you look at you
know this this one um and keep in mind I
think it's important to mention that I
didn't use a different query for any of
these this is all the same query AC used
across all of these different models and
we still got different citations for the
same query okay so that shows you that
this is not exactly uh you know it
nothing is static and I think that's the
most important thing to take out of this
is like nothing is static in this
process so just be careful with any you
know very high conviction claims of
tracking accuracy. Okay. And then
another important thing is that most
tools even including the one that we're
building
um are using synthetic prompts. Okay.
And what is a synthetic prompt? It just
means that it is uh made up. Let's just
be let's just be honest here. Like uh if
it's synthetic, it's just a madeup
prompt. Uh, and so you can make them
pretty, you know, what would be a
logical type of prompt that a a user
might use, but there's still no
quantifiable data to prove any of this.
Okay? So, every AI tracking tool, AI
search tracking tool is guessing right
now. Every single one because no one has
quantifiable data. Yes, you can look to
Google and get data from there, but it's
it's not there's not like, you know, you
search this one phrase here, which is I
need an SEO tool to check my website's
ranking for specific keywords. What do
you recommend? That whole query. We
don't know how many times people search
that. No one knows. Like literally, no
one knows how many times that is
searched on chat GBT or Perplexity or
Gemini. No one knows. Okay? And so it
still is important to track, but just
want to be you very transparent here
that these are synthetic prompts and you
can go like right now this example here
is from Claude. Go into Claude, you can
have it generate synthetic prompts for
you and you can start to run these
queries manually to see where your brand
is popping up. You can do that, right?
So it is possible. Uh and then finally,
this is a very important one. Um a lot
of these tools claim that they can
extract citations from uh AI generated
responses.
It is possible via API uh in chat GBT.
However, some of the other platforms you
actually can't do that. So, a lot of
them, uh, a lot of these tools, they're
claiming that they're showing you the
citations that are being used, but the
reality is is that they're mirroring
what one of these LLM would do. Okay,
I'm not going to get into this this
super like technical, but they are you
they're trying to mirror what an LL LLM
would do. And what an LLM would do is it
just goes to search to enhance its
response, right? So, for example, if you
use the 40 model, it's a couple years
old at this point. So, if you search
something that you you need a response
that's more current, it has to go to the
internet and in most cases when it goes
and retrieves, it's just going to go to
public search engines. Um, as of right
now, there's some debate about what chat
GBT uses, but as you know, they have a
partnership with Microsoft, which means
they we know for sure they can use Bing.
There's some evidence that they are
possibly using Google. Um and and we
know that like Claude tends to uh push
towards Brave search and then Perplexity
goes towards Bing quite a bit. Okay. So
the point is though public search
engines that and so if you the way these
tools work is they're just kind of
modeling what an LLM would do. They're
extracting citations from the top
ranking results anywhere between
positions one and 20. They're bringing
that back in and they're enhancing their
prompt and then they're saying here are
the citations that were used. That's not
necessarily the citations that were used
directly in a real life user scenario.
Okay? Because no one has access to that
information. No one can see real user
response like real user scenarios, real
user conversations. Okay? other than
that leak that just happened with Google
where you could see the shared uh
conversations but other than that that's
there it just doesn't exist at this
point. Um now there is some like kind of
sketchier things that tools can do which
is like using proxies and stuff but and
creating like thousands of chat GBT
accounts and running stuff through
there. They can do that but that's
against you know terms of service and
they're probably going to get banned. So
I wouldn't use a tool that's doing
anything sketchy like that. Okay. So
what should you do after all of that?
after I just threw the kitchen sink at
you. Um, what should you do? Well,
number one,
um, be very careful about
personalization.
But more importantly, remember what the
goals are of tracking. What What are we
even tracking in the first place? What
what are we doing here? How do we decide
what's a good idea to track? Well,
number one, what you're seeing here,
this is the most important thing to
track. And this is also the thing that
uh doesn't track well back to the
website and to a direct conversion. So
for example, what we're looking at here
is there's no links like there's no
links here. So you know uh but but the
thing is if we're not showing up in this
list that's a problem. Okay? And so we
need our brand to appear in the
generated responses. This is the most
important thing because when someone is
searching these commercial queries, we
need our brand to show up. We need our
clients brands to show up. Okay, that is
critical. So, this should be tracked all
the time and we should be doing it to
ensure that we're actually showing up in
the these responses. And if we're not,
we need to take the steps to do that.
Okay. Um, and now the question is like
how does this how do we quantify this
particular thing? Well, you know, how do
you quantify not being there? Right?
That's something that should be talked
about. Like a lot of people are talking,
well, how do if we're here, how do we
gen, you know, how do we, you know,
track the conversions? Well, you're
first of all, you're not because anyone
that claims that attribution, like real
attribution is even possible at this
point is just selling you nonsense.
Attribution is almost impossible. like
true attribution unless you have a
really um segmented siloed out funnel,
it's really really hard because the way
people use just tools and different
platforms these days is quite erratic,
right? Someone watches a YouTube video,
then they go to chat GBT, then they go
to Reddit, then they go to X, then they
go to LinkedIn, and then six months
later they become a, you know, a lead.
How are you going to track that? It's
just impossible. So the point is though
we want to focus more on like okay are
we act do we have prominence in these
responses that's what matters okay and
then of course you want to think about
okay well how do we improve how do we
become the number one you know
recommended option in these responses
okay so first is overall visibility are
we actually just showing up in general
like are we just even appearing and if
you're not even doing that then you got
a lot of work to do but once you're
appearing then it's a different game of
trying to figure out like okay well how
do we get above some of these
competitors. Okay? And you start to
think about that and you start to
exploit those variables that can
influence that uh the AI to to make that
recommendation higher. Okay? So this is
what needs to be tracked. It's very very
important. And then you don't like
there's I've seen some AI search
tracking tools out there that like say
they have analytics like you you just go
into Google Analytics 4 and you can see
the data for free. Like there's no like
I don't know what would be the reason
for using the analytics for inside
another tool when you can just go into
Google Analytics and use it yourself.
It's literally right here available for
anyone uh to see. So you know you can
use a you even use Google uh Google
looker studio and like build a dashboard
for this too if you want. So just just
use Google Analytics 4. It's right here.
It's free. Uh okay. So now let's talk
about a quick formula. This is really
important. So, if you want to be able to
track this the right way and you want to
get within a certain level of certainty
that somewhat models what would happen
in let's say a real life scenario,
nothing is perfect by the way, but this
can get you closer to getting a better
idea. Okay, so here's kind of a formula
that we're using. Number one, prompt
diversity. Okay, so you want to have
many different variants that are used.
Okay. And obviously you got to be
careful with certain variants that would
cause the AI to give an answer that
obviously isn't going to be super
useful. Like for example, if you were to
do like, you know, Nike baseball cleat
review, it's just going to talk about
Nike. So like if you're a competitor of
Nike, that's not really a useful query,
right? So you don't want to use that.
You want to keep the you want to keep
the uh queries pretty broad. So keep
them more commercial intent, but without
without any brands inside of there.
We've tested this rigorously. It's just
it ends up getting weird data. So, just
stick to the broader level. Let's call
it um uh they they are not brand aware.
Let's just use it. Let's just use that
phrase. Okay? They're they're not brand
aware. Uh but they have commercial
intent. Okay? That's what I focus on.
So, it be best SEO tools would be the
seed and you would build out um you know
these synthetic prompts based on that
seed. Now, I recommend um having at
least 25 variants at least, probably
even more, okay? Because to you want to
kind of blanket every possibility to get
a broad idea of your overall visibility
across all these these prompts, okay?
And I'm talking on one platform. So if
you were just to do chat GBT, you would
run 25 unique queries across chat GBT
that are related to that that seed
keyword that you used, which then you
you turned into a natural language
synthetic prompt. Um, and then you would
see how your brand is performing across
all 25 to get a broad idea. Okay? So you
don't want to be thinking like, I'm just
going to track this one prompt and I'm
going to see where we're that's just
pointless. You should be looking at it
broadly and looking like across the
board like okay based on these 50 you
know unique queries that we ran we have
25% visibility across these these you
know queries. Okay that's a much better
kind of tracking mechanism than trying
to individually track prompts that may
not even be used really at all. So you
just want the goal here of tracking is
to get a broad idea of performance of
visibility. Okay. And then this is the
one that's really important is you
probably should run the same prompt
multiple times. You don't need to go
super crazy and do it like 25 times, but
maybe run it at least one more time. So
take that same exact query and run that
same exact query again. This can help
eliminate some of the variance that
might exist. Um if you do it three
times, you're going to be probably more
than enough, right? So essentially what
would happen is you would basically run
anywhere between 75 to 100 of these
individual chats with these unique
natural language prompts that are
synthetic. Okay, that will give you a
pretty good idea from one base seed
keyword how your brand is performing. I
mean it it'd be pretty hard to, you
know, not get a good idea from that. So
this is the way that we're doing it.
Everyone's got their own philosophy on
this, but for us, we're focused on the
brand element, okay? Like where is the
brand showing up in in the AI
recommendations and in the generated
response? I think that matters more.
Okay? And then you can also if you're
trying to figure out like, okay, what
are the types of queries that people
might use? There's is possibly some data
starting to pop in that we could maybe
use. Okay. So, go into Google Search
Console and filter by slashoverview or
filter by slash search. Okay. I cannot
prove what I'm about to say, but I do
think this is a this is, you know, it is
telling. Okay, let's just say that much.
So, like on the overview, I'm totally
making an assumption that this is AI
overviews. Okay, just just possibly. I'm
not sure. I can't prove it once again,
but it seems quite likely that these
would be AI overview queries because of
the the how they're structured, what
they look like. They're long. They mimic
what someone would do in a large
language model. So, I would, you know,
be looking at these at least and kind of
investigate. And then on the right hand
side, we have slash search. So, these
are, in my opinion, once again, I cannot
prove this. It it looks like this could
be AI mode. I'm not sure because it
looks like it's a segmented out product
from Google so that it can segment from
traditional search. So that's just what
my opinion is like. I'm thinking in
terms of like what a SAS company would
do, this probably seems likely. Also,
given the nature of the queries, right?
These queries are much more natural
language. They're much longer. Um they
fit they fit the the criteria. Okay? So
you can start looking into this data in
Google search console and if you find
ones that don't look super synthetic
that look kind of pretty natural then
those would be ones you'd want to add to
your kind of you know your database of
prompts so that you can kind of uh get
more
uh get more education about how your
brand is showing up. Okay. So but the
key here is really do it based on
clusters. Okay. So, pick one seed maybe
for one of your core products and build
out, you know, let's say 25 to 100 of
these variants around your core product
and then you should be tracking those
around your one core product and you do
the same thing for another product. You
repeat that. So, that means you're going
to be tracking a lot. Um, but that's
really the you need a lot of surface
area to really get a good idea of how
you're performing. Okay? And then, uh,
as I mentioned before, run the same
prompt multiple times. Very, very
important.
Now, we are building uh Rankability AI
analyzer. So, if you want to get early
access to it, um the cool thing about
this is this is not going to be like an
add-on to Rankability. This is going to
be included into your core membership.
So, if you do go and sign up for
Rankability, obviously, we have some we
have, in my opinion, the best content
optimization tool that exists, but um
we're also adding this in here as well.
So just go to rankability.com and you
can get uh early access to this, but
we're going to focus purely on chat GBT
initially just because it has about 60%
of the large language model market. So
hope that helps. I know I kind of like
threw the kitchen sink at you, but it's
just important to understand how these
tools work and kind of the this the the
nature of AI search tracking. It is not
a perfect science by any means, but I
hope this helped and thank you so much
for watching.